Inventory of the Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo papers
1943-1980
88020
Hoover Institution Archives
100 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, memorabilia (48.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches, reports, notes, financial and legal records, and printed matter relating to political conditions in Cuba, Cuban political prisoners and emigrants, political and other activities of Hispanic Americans, Republican Party activities (especially during the administration of Richard M. Nixon), and the National Republican Heritage Groups Council.
Giberga Angulo, Manuel Rafael, 1916-1974.
Access
Collection is open for research. Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1916 Born, Havana, Cuba
1958 Left Cuba and settled in the United States
1959-1970 Worked as a business consultant to the sugar industry and various construction companies
1963 Became an American citizen
1968 Appointed by President Richard Nixon to the Committee on Opportunities for Spanish Speaking People
1971-1974 Served on the National Republican Heritage Groups Council
1974 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo papers document the political and professional careers of a Cuban American prominent in the late 1960s and early 1970s. Appointed by Richard M. Nixon as vice president of the Agency for Equal Opportunity for Spanish Speaking Americans, Giberga Angulo was also a member of the National Republican Heritage Groups Council. He acted as general liaison with the Cuban American community for the Nixon administration and was active in enlisting Cuban American support for the Republican Party. Giberga Angulo's papers include significant materials relating to Cuban refugees and to Cuban exile organizations opposed to the government of Fidel Castro. There is also a substantial amount of correspondence and printed matter pertaining to Cuban American community life, especially in Florida.
Following Giberga Angulo's death in 1974, his wife Lillian Giberga was appointed to succeed him in his official posts, and the papers include correspondence and other materials concerning her activities. The papers also contain materials relating to Giberga Angulo's career as a business consultant to the sugar industry and a number of construction companies. There is also a significant amount of materials concerning another of Giberga Angulo's business interests, the breeding and sale of thoroughbred horses.
Cuba--Politics and government--1959-1990.; Political prisoners--Cuba.; Cuban Americans.; Hispanic Americans.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); National Republican Heritage Groups Council.
- Curriculum vitae, 1971 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and reports, 1965-1973
- Clippings relating to Cuba and Cuban Americans, 1971
- Notebook, 1971
- Correspondence, 1961-1971 (Box 2)
- Business reports, 1961-1970
- Cables and printed matter relating to thoroughbred horses, 1968-1970
- Notebook, 1966
- Correspondence, 1961-1973 (Box 3)
- Clippings and newsletters relating to Cuba, 1960-1970
- Printed matter relating to thoroughbred horses, 1969-1970
- Business reports, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
- Partnership proposal for breeding thoroughbred horses, 1969
- Correspondence, clippings, and interview relating to the Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs, 1973 (Box 5)
- Correspondence and reports relating to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for Spanish Speaking People, 1973
- Photographs, correspondence, and records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1965-1968
- Reports relating to the sugar industry, 1962-1964 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, financial records, photographs, and printed matter relating to thoroughbred horses, 1966-1968
- Reports on migrant workers, 1971
- Case files on Cuban refugees, 1971
- Reports relating to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for Spanish Speaking People, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
- Reports on drug abuse, 1970
- Reports relating to Cuban exile organizations, 1971
- Business reports, 1965-1970
- Correspondence and case files relating to Cuban refugees, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
- Correspondence and photographs relating to thoroughbred horses, 1962-1968
- Programs and reports relating to the American Revolution Bicentennial Administration, 1975
- Clippings relating to the Puerto Rican population in Cleveland, Ohio, 1971
- Pamphlets relating to Cuba and communism, 1960-1976 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, case files, and mailing lists relating to Cuban refugees, 1971-1972
- Business correspondence and reports, 1967-1968 (Box 10)
- Printed matter relating to Cuban exile organizations, 1961
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972-1973
- Clippings relating to the Nixon administration and the Watergate Affair, 1972 (Box 11)
- Correspondence relating to the National Republican Heritage Organizations (Nationalities) Council, 1971
- Correspondence relating to thoroughbred horses, 1964-1966
- Correspondence and printed matter relating to Cuban refugees and Cuban exile organizations, 1961-1972 (Box 12)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1962-1968
- Correspondence and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1964
- Correspondence and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1964-1969 (Boxes 13-15)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1961-1964 (Box 16)
- Correspondence and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans, 1972-1973
- Clippings and correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1962-1973 (Box 17)
- Business reports, 1964-1967
- Business correspondence and reports, 1965-1975 (Box 18)
- Report by Giberga Angulo to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for the Spanish Speaking, 1971
- Correspondence, report, and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans, 1962-1974
- Correspondence relating to Cuba, Cuban refugees, and Cuban American organizations, 1965-1974 (Box 19)
- Correspondence relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1971-1972
- Speech by Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1971 (Box 20)
- Correspondence relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1971-1972
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1971-1973
- Congratulatory telegrams, 1971 (Box 21)
- Correspondence relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1972
- Correspondence relating to Cuban Americans, 1970-1972
- Printed matter relating to Cuban exile organizations, 1972 (Box 22)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban Americans, 1970-1972
- Contracts relating to Cuban refugees, 1972
- 1971-1976 (Boxes 23-24)
- Business reports, 1969 (Box 25)
- Clippings and printed matter relating to Cuba, Cuban Americans, and Latin America, 1960-1972
- Cuban National Planning Council reports, 1973 (Box 26)
- Business reports, 1963
- Reports on drug abuse, migrant workers, and mental health, 1970-1973
- Clippings and printed matter relating to Cuba, Cuban Americans, and Latin America, 1971-1974 (Box 27)
- Photographs depicting Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1970 (Box 28)
- Printed matter relating to Cuban Americans and the Republican and Democratic national conventions, 1972
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees and the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1972-1974 (Box 29)
- Printed matter relating to Cuban exile organizations and the sugar industry, 1962-1971
- Issues of Congressional Record, 1961-1975 (Box 30)
- Applications and curricula vitae relating to applications for government jobs, 1971
- Letter from Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo to Clarence M. Kelly, 1974
- Correspondence relating to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo's appointment to the Advisory Council to the Cabinet Committee for Spanish Speaking Americans, 1971 (Box 31)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Cuban Americans, 1971-1973
- Photographs depicting Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1972
- Letters of condolence sent to Lillian Giberga on the death of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974 (Box 32)
- Clippings relating to the career of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1973
- Clippings, obituaries, and announcements relating to the death of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974 (Box 33)
- Correspondence relating to Lillian M. Giberga and the Cuban Refugee Program, 1975
- Business reports, 1969 (Box 34)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1971-1973
- Correspondence relating to thoroughbred horses, 1970
- Correspondence and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1965-1966 (Box 35)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban Americans, 1971-1973
- Correspondence and photographs relating to thoroughbred horses, 1964-1968 (Box 36)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1968
- Correspondence and printed matter relating to Cuba, Cuban refugees, and Cuban exile groups, 1960-1972
- Correspondence relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1971-1974 (Box 37)
- Printed matter relating to Latin America, 1960-1962
- Correspondence relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1971-1972
- Writings and notes by Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1965-1972 (Box 38)
- Business correspondence, 1973
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1967-1968
- Printed matter relating to Cuba, 1960-1961
- Printed matter relating to Cuba and Latin America, 1960-1961 (Box 39)
- Business cables, 1962-1963
- Notebooks, 1971
- Business correspondence, 1962-1971 (Box 40)
- Clippings and printed matter relating to Cuba, Cuban Americans, and Cuban exile organizations, 1960-1972
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972-1974
- Reports relating to the Republican National Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 41)
- Clippings and printed matter relating to Cuba and Latin America, 1959-1978
- Reports relating to thoroughbred horses, 1964-1968
- Business correspondence, 1962-1973 (Box 42)
- Clippings and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1961-1974
- Notes on narcotics investigations, 1973
- Curriculum vitae, 1971 (Box 43)
- Correspondence with Laszlo Pastor, 1971-1973
- Printed matter relating to Cuba and Cuban Americans, 1961-1972
- Business correspondence and reports, 1959-1961 (Box 44)
- Printed matter relating to Cuba and Cuban exile organizations, 1960-1961
- Racing records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1964
- Correspondence and printed matter relating to Cuban refugees and Cuban exile organizations, 1962-1972 (Box 45)
- Correspondence relating to the Advisory Council on Spanish Speaking Americans, 1971
- Clippings relating to American politics, 1969
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1971-1972 (Box 46)
- Clippings relating to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1972-1973
- Correspondence and reports relating to Cuban exile organizations, 1961-1972 (Box 47)
- Clippings relating to Cuba and Cuban Americans, 1972-1974
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuban refugees and Cuban exile organizations, 1971-1973 (Box 48)
- Correspondence relating to the Republican National Committee, 1972-1973
- Clippings and serial issues relating to the Watergate Affair, 1973 (Box 49)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to the death of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974 (Box 50)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Cuban Americans, 1971-1972
- Business reports, 1973
- Correspondence and serial issues relating to Cuba, Cuban Americans, and Cuban exile organizations, 1959-1971 (Box 51)
- Cuban passport belonging to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1954
- Correspondence relating to the Advisory Council on Spanish Speaking Americans, 1971-1972 (Box 52)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to the Cuban Refugee Program, Cuban Americans, and Cuban exile organizations, 1969-1973
- Business reports, 1968
- Correspondence relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1973 (Box 53)
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga, 1974
- Correspondence and serial issues relating to Cuban Americans, 1971-1974
- Business correspondence and reports, 1962-1969 (Box 54)
- Racing records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1960-1962
- Printed matter and reports relating to the Republican National Committee and the 1972 presidential campaign (Box 55)
- Lists of naturalized citizens, 1971 (Box 56)
- Election results and analysis for Dade County, Florida, 1972
- Lists of naturalized citizens, 1972 (Box 57)
- Election results for Dade County, Florida, 1972
- Reports relating to the Republican National Committee, 1972
- Report and application relating to the Manuel Giberga Center for the Preservation of Cuban Culture, 1974 (Box 58)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972
- Statement made by Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo to the Platform Committee of the Republican National Convention, 1972
- Correspondence relating to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for the Spanish Speaking, 1973-1974
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972 (Box 59)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972 (Box 60)
- Correspondence and reports relating to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for the Spanish Speaking, 1971-1973
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Alberto Díaz Masvidal, 1970-1971
- Business correspondence and reports, 1960-1964 (Box 61)
- Business reports, 1962 (Box 62)
- Clippings and printed matter relating to Cuba and Cuban exile organizations, 1960-1973
- Correspondence relating to Cuban Americans, 1973
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972 (Box 63)
- Clippings relating to the Nixon administration, 1972 (Box 64)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1961-1969
- Correspondence relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1962-1973
- Business correspondence and reports, 1963-1969 (Box 65)
- Correspondence and report relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1973
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga, 1975-1976
- Clippings relating to American politics, 1972-1973
- Appointment book and notebooks, 1963-1973 (Box 66)
- Correspondence relating to the Asociación de Escritores y Artistas Americanos, 1967-1969
- Business reports, 1963-1969
- Reports relating to the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1971-1975
- Issues of Congressional Record, 1961 (Box 67)
- Business reports, 1967-1969
- Report relating to Cuba, 1961
- Business correspondence and reports, 1962-1969 (Box 68)
- Correspondence and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1967-1968
- Correspondence, printed matter, and racing and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1963-1966 (Box 69)
- Correspondence, printed matter, and sales and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1951-1966 (Box 70)
- Correspondence, photographs, and racing and breeding records relating to thoroughbred horses, 1959-1966 (Box 71)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972 (Box 72)
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972 (Box 73)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1962
- Correspondence, photographs, and printed matter relating to thoroughbred horses, 1965-1966
- Correspondence relating to Cuban refugees, 1972 (Box 74)
- Business report, 1967
- Clippings and photograph relating to thoroughbred horses, 1967
- Issues of Congressional Record, 1961 (Box 75)
- Transcripts of United States Senate hearings, 1960-1973
- Compilation of names of Cuban Americans, 1972 (Box 76)
- Award from President Nixon, "Free Cuba Forces" chart, and drawing of bust, 1971 (Box 77)
- Nixon proclamations, signed poster of Giberga, and framed letters of recognition, 1971-1973
- Image of a plaque depicting Cuban coat of arms, presented to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo by the Cuban American Association of New Jersey, 1973
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1961-1973 (Box 78)
- Clippings relating to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1972-1974
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Lillian Giberga, 1974
- Business correspondence, 1962-1975 (Box 79)
- Correspondence relating to the Republican National Committee, 1973
- Correspondence, clippings, and report relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1960-1973
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuba, Cuban Americans, and Cuban exile organizations, 1960-1973 (Box 80)
- Business correspondence, 1963-1966
- Letters of condolence sent to Lillian Giberga on the death of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974-1975 (Box 81)
- Photographs depicting the funeral of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1971-1975
- Obituaries and other articles relating to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1973-1974 (Box 82)
- Correspondence and reports relating to the Cuban Refugee Program, 1975
- Photographs depicting Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1973
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuban Americans and Cuban exile organizations, 1972-1974 (Box 83)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1964-1965
- Correspondence and reports relating to National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1972-1973 (Box 84)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1965
- Business correspondence and reports, 1959-1964 (Box 85)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1962-1965 (Box 86)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1963-1965 (Box 87)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Cuban Americans, 1961-1973
- Correspondence and reports relating to the Manuel Giberga Foundation, 1975 (Box 88)
- Clippings relating to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1943-1973
- Business correspondence, 1963-1969
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuba, Cuban Americans, and Cuban exile organizations, 1960-1973 (Box 89)
- Business correspondence, 1962-1963
- Curriculum vitae, 1971
- Speeches by Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1970-1972 (Box 90)
- Correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to Cuba and Cuban Americans, 1960-1972
- Business correspondence, 1962-1969
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Cuban refugees and Cuban Americans, 1971-1973 (Box 91)
- Business correspondence, 1971
- Correspondence relating to the Republican National Committee, 1971-1973
- Correspondence relating to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for the Spanish Speaking, 1972 (Box 92)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Cuban refugees, Cuban Americans, and Cuban exile organizations, 1964-1973
- Business correspondence, 1960-1962
- Report relating to the Cabinet Committee on Opportunities for the Spanish Speaking, 1971 (Box 93)
- Clippings relating to Cuba and Latin America, 1961
- Transcripts of proceedings of the Organization of American States, 1974
- Business correspondence and reports, 1964-1965 (Boxes 94-95)
- Business correspondence and reports, 1958-1965 (Box 96)
- Five compact sound cassettes containing interviews with and speeches by Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1968-1973 (Box 97)
- Cuban passport belonging to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1956
- Address books, 1970-1973
- Business correspondence, 1962-1965
- Correspondence and printed matter relating to thoroughbred horses, 1967-1968 (Box 98)
- Letters of condolence received by Lillian Giberga on the death of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974 (Box 99)
- Clippings relating to Cuba and Cuban Americans, 1975-1979
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga and the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1974-1975
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga and the National Republican Heritage Groups (Nationalities) Council, 1974-1975 (Box 100)
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga and various Cuban American organizations, 1974-1980
- Speeches made by Lillian Giberga, 1974 (Box 101)
- Articles of incorporation and correspondence relating to the Manuel Giberga Foundation, 1975
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga and various Cuban American organizations, 1974-1980
- Clippings relating to the activities of Lillian Giberga, 1974 (Box 102)
- Letters of condolence received by Lillian Giberga on the death of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1974
- Correspondence relating to Lillian Giberga, various Cuban American organizations, and the Republican National Committee, 1974-1976
- Reports relating to the Loyola School, 1976
- Drawings, printed matter, and honorary diploma, 1967-1974 (Box 103)
- Signed photograph of Richard M. Nixon, with an inscription to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo, 1970
- Album of clippings relating to the activities of Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo and Lillian Giberga, 1973-1974
- Album of photographs depicting Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo at an award ceremony in his honor, 1972 (Box 104)
- Compilations of names of Cuban Americans, 1972
- Photographs depicting Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo with Spiro Agnew, Barry Goldwater, and other individuals, 1958-1973 (Box 105)
- Envelope of Giberga's loose business cards
- Memorabilia, 1973 (On-shelf shelf)
  Scope and Contents note
  Plaque depicting Cuban coat of arms, presented to Manuel Rafael Giberga Angulo by the Cuban American Association of New Jersey. See Box 77 for an access image.